owad.de 2019-06-14

# OWAD - One Word A Day

## What my lawyer told me to also tell you

German Version below.

## Privacy Policy

## 1\. An overview of data protection

### General

The following gives a simple overview of what happens to your personal information when you visit our website. Personal information is any data with which you could be personally identified. Detailed information on the subject of data protection can be found in our privacy policy found below.

### Data collection on our website

**Who is responsible for the data collection on this website?**

The data collected on this website are processed by the website operator. The operator's contact details can be found in the website's required legal notice.

**How do we collect your data?**

Some data are collected when you provide it to us. This could, for example, be data you enter on a contact form.

Other data are collected automatically by our IT systems when you visit the website. These data are primarily technical data such as the browser and operating system you are using or when you accessed the page. These data are collected automatically as soon as you enter our website.

**What do we use your data for?**

Part of the data is collected to ensure the proper functioning of the website. Other data can be used to analyze how visitors use the site.

**What rights do you have regarding your data?**

You always have the right to request information about your stored data, its origin, its recipients, and the purpose of its collection at no charge. You also have the right to request that it be corrected, blocked, or deleted. You can contact us at any time using the address given in the legal notice if you have further questions about the issue of privacy and data protection. You may also, of course, file a complaint with the competent regulatory authorities.

### Analytics and third-party tools

When visiting our website, statistical analyses may be made of your surfing behavior. This happens primarily using cookies and analytics. The analysis of your surfing behavior is usually anonymous, i.e. we will not be able to identify you from this data. You can object to this analysis or prevent it by not using certain tools. Detailed information can be found in the following privacy policy.

You can object to this analysis. We will inform you below about how to exercise your options in this regard.

## 2\. General information and mandatory information

### Data protection

The operators of this website take the protection of your personal data very seriously. We treat your personal data as confidential and in accordance with the statutory data protection regulations and this privacy policy.

If you use this website, various pieces of personal data will be collected. Personal information is any data with which you could be personally identified. This privacy policy explains what information we collect and what we use it for. It also explains how and for what purpose this happens.

Please note that data transmitted via the internet (e.g. via email communication) may be subject to security breaches. Complete protection of your data from third-party access is not possible.

### Notice concerning the party responsible for this website

The party responsible for processing data on this website is:

Paul Smith Associates GmbH & Co. KG  
Schulweg 51,   
87775 Salgen

Telephone: 0049 (0) 8266 1071  
Email: psa@smith.de

The responsible party is the natural or legal person who alone or jointly with others decides on the purposes and means of processing personal data (names, email addresses, etc.).

### Revocation of your consent to the processing of your data

Many data processing operations are only possible with your express consent. You may revoke your consent at any time with future effect. An informal email making this request is sufficient. The data processed before we receive your request may still be legally processed.

### Right to data portability

You have the right to have data which we process based on your consent or in fulfillment of a contract automatically delivered to yourself or to a third party in a standard, machine-readable format. If you require the direct transfer of data to another responsible party, this will only be done to the extent technically feasible.

### SSL or TLS encryption

This site uses SSL or TLS encryption for security reasons and for the protection of the transmission of confidential content, such as the inquiries you send to us as the site operator. You can recognize an encrypted connection in your browser's address line when it changes from "http://" to "https://" and the lock icon is displayed in your browser's address bar.

If SSL or TLS encryption is activated, the data you transfer to us cannot be read by third parties.

### Information, blocking, deletion

As permitted by law, you have the right to be provided at any time with information free of charge about any of your personal data that is stored as well as its origin, the recipient and the purpose for which it has been processed. You also have the right to have this data corrected, blocked or deleted. You can contact us at any time using the address given in our legal notice if you have further questions on the topic of personal data.

### Opposition to promotional emails

We hereby expressly prohibit the use of contact data published in the context of website legal notice requirements with regard to sending promotional and informational materials not expressly requested. The website operator reserves the right to take specific legal action if unsolicited advertising material, such as email spam, is received.

## 3\. Data collection on our website

### Cookies

Some of our web pages use cookies. Cookies do not harm your computer and do not contain any viruses. Cookies help make our website more user-friendly, efficient, and secure. Cookies are small text files that are stored on your computer and saved by your browser.

Most of the cookies we use are so-called "session cookies." They are automatically deleted after your visit. Other cookies remain in your device's memory until you delete them. These cookies make it possible to recognize your browser when you next visit the site.

You can configure your browser to inform you about the use of cookies so that you can decide on a case-by-case basis whether to accept or reject a cookie. Alternatively, your browser can be configured to automatically accept cookies under certain conditions or to always reject them, or to automatically delete cookies when closing your browser. Disabling cookies may limit the functionality of this website.

Cookies which are necessary to allow electronic communications or to provide certain functions you wish to use (such as the shopping cart) are stored pursuant to Art. 6 paragraph 1, letter f of DSGVO. The website operator has a legitimate interest in the storage of cookies to ensure an optimized service provided free of technical errors. If other cookies (such as those used to analyze your surfing behavior) are also stored, they will be treated separately in this privacy policy.

### Server log files

The website provider automatically collects and stores information that your browser automatically transmits to us in "server log files". These are:

  * Browser type and browser version
  * Operating system used
  * Referrer URL
  * Host name of the accessing computer
  * Time of the server request
  * IP address

These data will not be combined with data from other sources.

The basis for data processing is Art. 6 (1) (f) DSGVO, which allows the processing of data to fulfill a contract or for measures preliminary to a contract.

### Contact form

Should you send us questions via the contact form, we will collect the data entered on the form, including the contact details you provide, to answer your question and any follow-up questions. We do not share this information without your permission.

We will, therefore, process any data you enter onto the contact form only with your consent per Art. 6 (1)(a) DSGVO. You may revoke your consent at any time. An informal email making this request is sufficient. The data processed before we receive your request may still be legally processed.

We will retain the data you provide on the contact form until you request its deletion, revoke your consent for its storage, or the purpose for its storage no longer pertains (e.g. after fulfilling your request). Any mandatory statutory provisions, especially those regarding mandatory data retention periods, remain unaffected by this provision.

### Registration on this website

You can register on our website in order to access additional functions offered here. The input data will only be used for the purpose of using the respective site or service for which you have registered. The mandatory information requested during registration must be provided in full. Otherwise, we will reject your registration.

To inform you about important changes such as those within the scope of our site or technical changes, we will use the email address specified during registration.

We will process the data provided during registration only based on your consent per Art. 6 (1)(a) DSGVO. You may revoke your consent at any time with future effect. An informal email making this request is sufficient. The data processed before we receive your request may still be legally processed.

We will continue to store the data collected during registration for as long as you remain registered on our website. Statutory retention periods remain unaffected.

### Leaving comments on this website

If you use the comment function on this site, the time at which you created the comment and your email address will be stored along with your comment, as well as your username, unless you are posting anonymously.

**Storage of the IP address**

Our comment function stores the IP addresses of those users who post comments. Since we do not check comments on our site before they go live, we need this information to be able to pursue action for illegal or slanderous content.

**Subscribing to the comment feed**

As a user of this site, you can sign up to receive the comment feed after registering. Your email address will be checked with a confirmation email. You can unsubscribe from this function at any time by clicking the link in the emails. The data provided when you subscribed to the comments feed will then be deleted, but if you have submitted this data to us for other purposes or elsewhere (such as subscribing to a newsletter), it will be retained.

**How long comments are stored**

The comments and the associated data (e.g. IP address) are stored and remain on our website until the content commented upon has been completely deleted or the comments are required to be removed for legal reasons (slander, etc.).

**Legal basis**

The comments are stored based on your consent per Art. 6 (1) (a) DSGVO. You may revoke your consent at any time with future effect. An informal email making this request is sufficient. The data processed before we receive your request may still be legally processed.

### Processing of data (customer and contract data)

We collect, process, and use personal data only insofar as it is necessary to establish, or modify legal relationships with us (master data). This is done based on Art. 6 (1) (b) DSGVO, which allows the processing of data to fulfill a contract or for measures preliminary to a contract. We collect, process and use your personal data when accessing our website (usage data) only to the extent required to enable you to access our service or to bill you for the same.

Collected customer data shall be deleted after completion of the order or termination of the business relationship. Legal retention periods remain unaffected.

### Data transmitted when entering into a contract with online shops, retailers, and mail order

We transmit personally identifiable data to third parties only to the extent required to fulfill the terms of your contract, for example, to companies entrusted to deliver goods to your location or banks entrusted to process your payments. Your data will not be transmitted for any other purpose unless you have given your express permission to do so. Your data will not be disclosed to third parties for advertising purposes without your express consent.

The basis for data processing is Art. 6 (1) (b) DSGVO, which allows the processing of data to fulfill a contract or for measures preliminary to a contract.

### Data transferred when signing up for services and digital content

We transmit personally identifiable data to third parties only to the extent required to fulfill the terms of your contract with us, for example, to banks entrusted to process your payments.

Your data will not be transmitted for any other purpose unless you have given your express permission to do so. Your data will not be disclosed to third parties for advertising purposes without your express consent.

The basis for data processing is Art. 6 (1) (b) DSGVO, which allows the processing of data to fulfill a contract or for measures preliminary to a contract.

## 4\. Analytics and advertising

### Google Analytics

This website uses Google Analytics, a web analytics service. It is operated by Google Inc., 1600 Amphitheatre Parkway, Mountain View, CA 94043, USA.

Google Analytics uses so-called "cookies". These are text files that are stored on your computer and that allow an analysis of the use of the website by you. The information generated by the cookie about your use of this website is usually transmitted to a Google server in the USA and stored there.

Google Analytics cookies are stored based on Art. 6 (1) (f) DSGVO. The website operator has a legitimate interest in analyzing user behavior to optimize both its website and its advertising.

**Browser plugin**

You can prevent these cookies being stored by selecting the appropriate settings in your browser. However, we wish to point out that doing so may mean you will not be able to enjoy the full functionality of this website. You can also prevent the data generated by cookies about your use of the website (incl. your IP address) from being passed to Google, and the processing of these data by Google, by downloading and installing the browser plugin available at the following link: <https://tools.google.com/dlpage/gaoptout?hl=en>.

**Objecting to the collection of data**

You can prevent the collection of your data by Google Analytics by clicking on the following link. An opt-out cookie will be set to prevent your data from being collected on future visits to this site: Disable Google Analytics.

For more information about how Google Analytics handles user data, see Google's privacy policy: <https://support.google.com/analytics/answer/6004245?hl=en>.

 **Outsourced data processing**

We have entered into an agreement with Google for the outsourcing of our data processing and fully implement the strict requirements of the German data protection authorities when using Google Analytics.

**Demographic data collection by Google Analytics**

This website uses Google Analytics' demographic features. This allows reports to be generated containing statements about the age, gender, and interests of site visitors. This data comes from interest-based advertising from Google and third-party visitor data. This collected data cannot be attributed to any specific individual person. You can disable this feature at any time by adjusting the ads settings in your Google account or you can forbid the collection of your data by Google Analytics as described in the section "Refusal of data collection".

## 5\. Newsletter

### Newsletter data

If you would like to receive our newsletter, we require a valid email address as well as information that allows us to verify that you are the owner of the specified email address and that you agree to receive this newsletter. No additional data is collected or is only collected on a voluntary basis. We only use this data to send the requested information and do not pass it on to third parties.

We will, therefore, process any data you enter onto the contact form only with your consent per Art. 6 (1) (a) DSGVO. You can revoke consent to the storage of your data and email address as well as their use for sending the newsletter at any time, e.g. through the "unsubscribe" link in the newsletter. The data processed before we receive your request may still be legally processed.

The data provided when registering for the newsletter will be used to distribute the newsletter until you cancel your subscription when said data will be deleted. Data we have stored for other purposes (e.g. email addresses for the members area) remain unaffected.

### MailChimp

This website uses the services of MailChimp to send newsletters. This service is provided by Rocket Science Group LLC, 675 Ponce De Leon Ave NE, Suite 5000, Atlanta, GA 30308, USA.

MailChimp is a service which organizes and analyzes the distribution of newsletters. If you provide data (e.g. your email address) to subscribe to our newsletter, it will be stored on MailChimp servers in the USA.

MailChimp is certified under the EU-US Privacy Shield. The Privacy Shield is an agreement between the European Union (EU) and the US to ensure compliance with European privacy standards in the United States.

We use MailChimp to analyze our newsletter campaigns. When you open an email sent by MailChimp, a file included in the email (called a web beacon) connects to MailChimp's servers in the United States. This allows us to determine if a newsletter message has been opened and which links you click on. In addition, technical information is collected (e.g. time of retrieval, IP address, browser type, and operating system). This information cannot be assigned to a specific recipient. It is used exclusively for the statistical analysis of our newsletter campaigns. The results of these analyses can be used to better tailor future newsletters to your interests.

If you do not want your usage of the newsletter to be analyzed by MailChimp, you will have to unsubscribe from the newsletter. For this purpose, we provide a link in every newsletter we send. You can also unsubscribe from the newsletter directly on the website.

Data processing is based on Art. 6 (1) (a) DSGVO. You may revoke your consent at any time by unsubscribing to the newsletter. The data processed before we receive your request may still be legally processed.

The data provided when registering for the newsletter will be used to distribute the newsletter until you cancel your subscription when said data will be deleted from our servers and those of MailChimp. Data we have stored for other purposes (e.g. email addresses for the members area) remains unaffected.

For details, see the MailChimp privacy policy at <https://mailchimp.com/legal/terms/>.

**Completion of a data processing agreement**

We have entered into a data processing agreement with MailChimp, in which we require MailChimp to protect the data of our customers and not to disclose said data to third parties. This agreement may be viewed at the following link: <https://mailchimp.com/legal/forms/data-processing-agreement/sample-agreement/>.

### Sparkpost

This website uses the services of Sparkpost to send newsletters. This service is provided by Sparkpost Inc., 301 Howard St #1330, San Francisco, CA 94105, USA.

Sparkpost is a service which organizes and analyzes the distribution of newsletters. If you provide data (e.g. your email address) to subscribe to our newsletter, it will be stored on Sparkpost servers in the USA.

Sparkpost is certified under the EU-US Privacy Shield. The Privacy Shield is an agreement between the European Union (EU) and the US to ensure compliance with European privacy standards in the United States.

We use Sparkpost to analyze our newsletter campaigns. When you open an email sent by Sparkpost, a file included in the email (called a web beacon) connects to Sparkpost's servers in the United States. This allows us to determine if a newsletter message has been opened and which links you click on. In addition, technical information is collected (e.g. time of retrieval, IP address, browser type, and operating system). This information cannot be assigned to a specific recipient. It is used exclusively for the statistical analysis of our newsletter campaigns. The results of these analyses can be used to better tailor future newsletters to your interests.

If you do not want your usage of the newsletter to be analyzed by Sparkpost, you will have to unsubscribe from the newsletter. For this purpose, we provide a link in every newsletter we send. You can also unsubscribe from the newsletter directly on the website.

Data processing is based on Art. 6 (1) (a) DSGVO. You may revoke your consent at any time by unsubscribing to the newsletter. The data processed before we receive your request may still be legally processed.

The data provided when registering for the newsletter will be used to distribute the newsletter until you cancel your subscription when said data will be deleted from our servers and those of Sparkpost. Data we have stored for other purposes (e.g. email addresses for the members area) remains unaffected.

For details, see the Sparkpost privacy policy at <https://www.sparkpost.com/policies/privacy/>.

**Completion of a data processing agreement**

We have entered into a data processing agreement with Sparkpost, in which we require Sparkpost to protect the data of our customers and not to disclose said data to third parties. 

## 6\. Plugins and tools

### Google Web Fonts

For uniform representation of fonts, this page uses web fonts provided by Google. When you open a page, your browser loads the required web fonts into your browser cache to display texts and fonts correctly.

For this purpose your browser has to establish a direct connection to Google servers. Google thus becomes aware that our web page was accessed via your IP address. The use of Google Web fonts is done in the interest of a uniform and attractive presentation of our website. This constitutes a justified interest pursuant to Art. 6 (1) (f) DSGVO.

If your browser does not support web fonts, a standard font is used by your computer.

Further information about handling user data, can be found at <https://developers.google.com/fonts/faq> and in Google's privacy policy at <https://www.google.com/policies/privacy/>.

## 7\. Payment service providers

### PayPal

Our website accepts payments via PayPal. The provider of this service is PayPal (Europe) S.à.r.l & Cie, S.C.A. (22-24 Boulevard Royal, L-2449 Luxembourg.

If you select payment via PayPal, the payment data you provide will be supplied to PayPal based on Art. 6 (1) (a) (Consent) and Art. 6 (1) (b) DSGVO (Processing for contract purposes). You have the option to revoke your consent at any time with future effect. It does not affect the processing of data previously collected.

## Datenschutzerklärung

## 1\. Datenschutz auf einen Blick

### Allgemeine Hinweise

Die folgenden Hinweise geben einen einfachen Überblick darüber, was mit Ihren personenbezogenen Daten passiert, wenn Sie unsere Website besuchen. Personenbezogene Daten sind alle Daten, mit denen Sie persönlich identifiziert werden können. Ausführliche Informationen zum Thema Datenschutz entnehmen Sie unserer unter diesem Text aufgeführten Datenschutzerklärung.

### Datenerfassung auf unserer Website

**Wer ist verantwortlich für die Datenerfassung auf dieser Website?**

Die Datenverarbeitung auf dieser Website erfolgt durch den Websitebetreiber. Dessen Kontaktdaten können Sie dem Impressum dieser Website entnehmen.

**Wie erfassen wir Ihre Daten?**

Ihre Daten werden zum einen dadurch erhoben, dass Sie uns diese mitteilen. Hierbei kann es sich z.B. um Daten handeln, die Sie in ein Kontaktformular eingeben.

Andere Daten werden automatisch beim Besuch der Website durch unsere IT-Systeme erfasst. Das sind vor allem technische Daten (z.B. Internetbrowser, Betriebssystem oder Uhrzeit des Seitenaufrufs). Die Erfassung dieser Daten erfolgt automatisch, sobald Sie unsere Website betreten.

**Wofür nutzen wir Ihre Daten?**

Ein Teil der Daten wird erhoben, um eine fehlerfreie Bereitstellung der Website zu gewährleisten. Andere Daten können zur Analyse Ihres Nutzerverhaltens verwendet werden.

**Welche Rechte haben Sie bezüglich Ihrer Daten?**

Sie haben jederzeit das Recht unentgeltlich Auskunft über Herkunft, Empfänger und Zweck Ihrer gespeicherten personenbezogenen Daten zu erhalten. Sie haben außerdem ein Recht, die Berichtigung, Sperrung oder Löschung dieser Daten zu verlangen. Hierzu sowie zu weiteren Fragen zum Thema Datenschutz können Sie sich jederzeit unter der im Impressum angegebenen Adresse an uns wenden. Des Weiteren steht Ihnen ein Beschwerderecht bei der zuständigen Aufsichtsbehörde zu.

### Analyse-Tools und Tools von Drittanbietern

Beim Besuch unserer Website kann Ihr Surf-Verhalten statistisch ausgewertet werden. Das geschieht vor allem mit Cookies und mit sogenannten Analyseprogrammen. Die Analyse Ihres Surf-Verhaltens erfolgt in der Regel anonym; das Surf-Verhalten kann nicht zu Ihnen zurückverfolgt werden. Sie können dieser Analyse widersprechen oder sie durch die Nichtbenutzung bestimmter Tools verhindern. Detaillierte Informationen dazu finden Sie in der folgenden Datenschutzerklärung.

Sie können dieser Analyse widersprechen. Über die Widerspruchsmöglichkeiten werden wir Sie in dieser Datenschutzerklärung informieren.

## 2\. Allgemeine Hinweise und Pflichtinformationen

### Datenschutz

Die Betreiber dieser Seiten nehmen den Schutz Ihrer persönlichen Daten sehr ernst. Wir behandeln Ihre personenbezogenen Daten vertraulich und entsprechend der gesetzlichen Datenschutzvorschriften sowie dieser Datenschutzerklärung.

Wenn Sie diese Website benutzen, werden verschiedene personenbezogene Daten erhoben. Personenbezogene Daten sind Daten, mit denen Sie persönlich identifiziert werden können. Die vorliegende Datenschutzerklärung erläutert, welche Daten wir erheben und wofür wir sie nutzen. Sie erläutert auch, wie und zu welchem Zweck das geschieht.

Wir weisen darauf hin, dass die Datenübertragung im Internet (z.B. bei der Kommunikation per E-Mail) Sicherheitslücken aufweisen kann. Ein lückenloser Schutz der Daten vor dem Zugriff durch Dritte ist nicht möglich.

### Hinweis zur verantwortlichen Stelle

Die verantwortliche Stelle für die Datenverarbeitung auf dieser Website ist:

Paul Smith Associates GmbH & Co. KG  
Schulweg 51,   
87775 Salgen

Telefon: 0049 (0) 8266 1071  
E-Mail: psa@smith.de

Verantwortliche Stelle ist die natürliche oder juristische Person, die allein oder gemeinsam mit anderen über die Zwecke und Mittel der Verarbeitung von personenbezogenen Daten (z.B. Namen, E-Mail-Adressen o. Ä.) entscheidet.

### Widerruf Ihrer Einwilligung zur Datenverarbeitung

Viele Datenverarbeitungsvorgänge sind nur mit Ihrer ausdrücklichen Einwilligung möglich. Sie können eine bereits erteilte Einwilligung jederzeit widerrufen. Dazu reicht eine formlose Mitteilung per E-Mail an uns. Die Rechtmäßigkeit der bis zum Widerruf erfolgten Datenverarbeitung bleibt vom Widerruf unberührt.

### Recht auf Datenübertragbarkeit

Sie haben das Recht, Daten, die wir auf Grundlage Ihrer Einwilligung oder in Erfüllung eines Vertrags automatisiert verarbeiten, an sich oder an einen Dritten in einem gängigen, maschinenlesbaren Format aushändigen zu lassen. Sofern Sie die direkte Übertragung der Daten an einen anderen Verantwortlichen verlangen, erfolgt dies nur, soweit es technisch machbar ist.

### SSL- bzw. TLS-Verschlüsselung

Diese Seite nutzt aus Sicherheitsgründen und zum Schutz der Übertragung vertraulicher Inhalte, wie zum Beispiel Bestellungen oder Anfragen, die Sie an uns als Seitenbetreiber senden, eine SSL-bzw. TLS-Verschlüsselung. Eine verschlüsselte Verbindung erkennen Sie daran, dass die Adresszeile des Browsers von “http://” auf “https://” wechselt und an dem Schloss-Symbol in Ihrer Browserzeile.

Wenn die SSL- bzw. TLS-Verschlüsselung aktiviert ist, können die Daten, die Sie an uns übermitteln, nicht von Dritten mitgelesen werden.

### Auskunft, Sperrung, Löschung

Sie haben im Rahmen der geltenden gesetzlichen Bestimmungen jederzeit das Recht auf unentgeltliche Auskunft über Ihre gespeicherten personenbezogenen Daten, deren Herkunft und Empfänger und den Zweck der Datenverarbeitung und ggf. ein Recht auf Berichtigung, Sperrung oder Löschung dieser Daten. Hierzu sowie zu weiteren Fragen zum Thema personenbezogene Daten können Sie sich jederzeit unter der im Impressum angegebenen Adresse an uns wenden.

### Widerspruch gegen Werbe-Mails

Der Nutzung von im Rahmen der Impressumspflicht veröffentlichten Kontaktdaten zur Übersendung von nicht ausdrücklich angeforderter Werbung und Informationsmaterialien wird hiermit widersprochen. Die Betreiber der Seiten behalten sich ausdrücklich rechtliche Schritte im Falle der unverlangten Zusendung von Werbeinformationen, etwa durch Spam-E-Mails, vor.

## 3\. Datenerfassung auf unserer Website

### Cookies

Die Internetseiten verwenden teilweise so genannte Cookies. Cookies richten auf Ihrem Rechner keinen Schaden an und enthalten keine Viren. Cookies dienen dazu, unser Angebot nutzerfreundlicher, effektiver und sicherer zu machen. Cookies sind kleine Textdateien, die auf Ihrem Rechner abgelegt werden und die Ihr Browser speichert.

Die meisten der von uns verwendeten Cookies sind so genannte “Session-Cookies”. Sie werden nach Ende Ihres Besuchs automatisch gelöscht. Andere Cookies bleiben auf Ihrem Endgerät gespeichert bis Sie diese löschen. Diese Cookies ermöglichen es uns, Ihren Browser beim nächsten Besuch wiederzuerkennen.

Sie können Ihren Browser so einstellen, dass Sie über das Setzen von Cookies informiert werden und Cookies nur im Einzelfall erlauben, die Annahme von Cookies für bestimmte Fälle oder generell ausschließen sowie das automatische Löschen der Cookies beim Schließen des Browser aktivieren. Bei der Deaktivierung von Cookies kann die Funktionalität dieser Website eingeschränkt sein.

Cookies, die zur Durchführung des elektronischen Kommunikationsvorgangs oder zur Bereitstellung bestimmter, von Ihnen erwünschter Funktionen (z.B. Warenkorbfunktion) erforderlich sind, werden auf Grundlage von Art. 6 Abs. 1 lit. f DSGVO gespeichert. Der Websitebetreiber hat ein berechtigtes Interesse an der Speicherung von Cookies zur technisch fehlerfreien und optimierten Bereitstellung seiner Dienste. Soweit andere Cookies (z.B. Cookies zur Analyse Ihres Surfverhaltens) gespeichert werden, werden diese in dieser Datenschutzerklärung gesondert behandelt.

### Server-Log-Dateien

Der Provider der Seiten erhebt und speichert automatisch Informationen in so genannten Server-Log-Dateien, die Ihr Browser automatisch an uns übermittelt. Dies sind:

  * Browsertyp und Browserversion
  * verwendetes Betriebssystem
  * Referrer URL
  * Hostname des zugreifenden Rechners
  * Uhrzeit der Serveranfrage
  * IP-Adresse

Eine Zusammenführung dieser Daten mit anderen Datenquellen wird nicht vorgenommen.

Grundlage für die Datenverarbeitung ist Art. 6 Abs. 1 lit. f DSGVO, der die Verarbeitung von Daten zur Erfüllung eines Vertrags oder vorvertraglicher Maßnahmen gestattet.

### Kontaktformular

Wenn Sie uns per Kontaktformular Anfragen zukommen lassen, werden Ihre Angaben aus dem Anfrageformular inklusive der von Ihnen dort angegebenen Kontaktdaten zwecks Bearbeitung der Anfrage und für den Fall von Anschlussfragen bei uns gespeichert. Diese Daten geben wir nicht ohne Ihre Einwilligung weiter.

Die Verarbeitung der in das Kontaktformular eingegebenen Daten erfolgt somit ausschließlich auf Grundlage Ihrer Einwilligung (Art. 6 Abs. 1 lit. a DSGVO). Sie können diese Einwilligung jederzeit widerrufen. Dazu reicht eine formlose Mitteilung per E-Mail an uns. Die Rechtmäßigkeit der bis zum Widerruf erfolgten Datenverarbeitungsvorgänge bleibt vom Widerruf unberührt.

Die von Ihnen im Kontaktformular eingegebenen Daten verbleiben bei uns, bis Sie uns zur Löschung auffordern, Ihre Einwilligung zur Speicherung widerrufen oder der Zweck für die Datenspeicherung entfällt (z.B. nach abgeschlossener Bearbeitung Ihrer Anfrage). Zwingende gesetzliche Bestimmungen – insbesondere Aufbewahrungsfristen – bleiben unberührt.

### Registrierung auf dieser Website

Sie können sich auf unserer Website registrieren, um zusätzliche Funktionen auf der Seite zu nutzen. Die dazu eingegebenen Daten verwenden wir nur zum Zwecke der Nutzung des jeweiligen Angebotes oder Dienstes, für den Sie sich registriert haben. Die bei der Registrierung abgefragten Pflichtangaben müssen vollständig angegeben werden. Anderenfalls werden wir die Registrierung ablehnen.

Für wichtige Änderungen etwa beim Angebotsumfang oder bei technisch notwendigen Änderungen nutzen wir die bei der Registrierung angegebene E-Mail-Adresse, um Sie auf diesem Wege zu informieren.

Die Verarbeitung der bei der Registrierung eingegebenen Daten erfolgt auf Grundlage Ihrer Einwilligung (Art. 6 Abs. 1 lit. a DSGVO). Sie können eine von Ihnen erteilte Einwilligung jederzeit widerrufen. Dazu reicht eine formlose Mitteilung per E-Mail an uns. Die Rechtmäßigkeit der bereits erfolgten Datenverarbeitung bleibt vom Widerruf unberührt.

Die bei der Registrierung erfassten Daten werden von uns gespeichert, solange Sie auf unserer Website registriert sind und werden anschließend gelöscht. Gesetzliche Aufbewahrungsfristen bleiben unberührt.

### Verarbeiten von Daten (Kunden- und Vertragsdaten)

Wir erheben, verarbeiten und nutzen personenbezogene Daten nur, soweit sie für die Begründung, inhaltliche Ausgestaltung oder Änderung des Rechtsverhältnisses erforderlich sind (Bestandsdaten). Dies erfolgt auf Grundlage von Art. 6 Abs. 1 lit. b DSGVO, der die Verarbeitung von Daten zur Erfüllung eines Vertrags oder vorvertraglicher Maßnahmen gestattet. Personenbezogene Daten über die Inanspruchnahme unserer Internetseiten (Nutzungsdaten) erheben, verarbeiten und nutzen wir nur, soweit dies erforderlich ist, um dem Nutzer die Inanspruchnahme des Dienstes zu ermöglichen oder abzurechnen.

Die erhobenen Kundendaten werden nach Abschluss des Auftrags oder Beendigung der Geschäftsbeziehung gelöscht. Gesetzliche Aufbewahrungsfristen bleiben unberührt.

### Datenübermittlung bei Vertragsschluss für Online-Shops, Händler und Warenversand

Wir übermitteln personenbezogene Daten an Dritte nur dann, wenn dies im Rahmen der Vertragsabwicklung notwendig ist, etwa an die mit der Lieferung der Ware betrauten Unternehmen oder das mit der Zahlungsabwicklung beauftragte Kreditinstitut. Eine weitergehende Übermittlung der Daten erfolgt nicht bzw. nur dann, wenn Sie der Übermittlung ausdrücklich zugestimmt haben. Eine Weitergabe Ihrer Daten an Dritte ohne ausdrückliche Einwilligung, etwa zu Zwecken der Werbung, erfolgt nicht.

Grundlage für die Datenverarbeitung ist Art. 6 Abs. 1 lit. b DSGVO, der die Verarbeitung von Daten zur Erfüllung eines Vertrags oder vorvertraglicher Maßnahmen gestattet.

### Datenübermittlung bei Vertragsschluss für Dienstleistungen und digitale Inhalte

Wir übermitteln personenbezogene Daten an Dritte nur dann, wenn dies im Rahmen der Vertragsabwicklung notwendig ist, etwa an das mit der Zahlungsabwicklung beauftragte Kreditinstitut.

Eine weitergehende Übermittlung der Daten erfolgt nicht bzw. nur dann, wenn Sie der Übermittlung ausdrücklich zugestimmt haben. Eine Weitergabe Ihrer Daten an Dritte ohne ausdrückliche Einwilligung, etwa zu Zwecken der Werbung, erfolgt nicht.

Grundlage für die Datenverarbeitung ist Art. 6 Abs. 1 lit. b DSGVO, der die Verarbeitung von Daten zur Erfüllung eines Vertrags oder vorvertraglicher Maßnahmen gestattet.

## 4\. Analyse Tools und Werbung

### Google Analytics

Diese Website nutzt Funktionen des Webanalysedienstes Google Analytics. Anbieter ist die Google Inc., 1600 Amphitheatre Parkway, Mountain View, CA 94043, USA.

Google Analytics verwendet so genannte "Cookies". Das sind Textdateien, die auf Ihrem Computer gespeichert werden und die eine Analyse der Benutzung der Website durch Sie ermöglichen. Die durch den Cookie erzeugten Informationen über Ihre Benutzung dieser Website werden in der Regel an einen Server von Google in den USA übertragen und dort gespeichert.

Die Speicherung von Google-Analytics-Cookies erfolgt auf Grundlage von Art. 6 Abs. 1 lit. f DSGVO. Der Websitebetreiber hat ein berechtigtes Interesse an der Analyse des Nutzerverhaltens, um sowohl sein Webangebot als auch seine Werbung zu optimieren.

**Browser Plugin**

Sie können die Speicherung der Cookies durch eine entsprechende Einstellung Ihrer Browser-Software verhindern; wir weisen Sie jedoch darauf hin, dass Sie in diesem Fall gegebenenfalls nicht sämtliche Funktionen dieser Website vollumfänglich werden nutzen können. Sie können darüber hinaus die Erfassung der durch den Cookie erzeugten und auf Ihre Nutzung der Website bezogenen Daten (inkl. Ihrer IP-Adresse) an Google sowie die Verarbeitung dieser Daten durch Google verhindern, indem Sie das unter dem folgenden Link verfügbare Browser-Plugin herunterladen und installieren: <https://tools.google.com/dlpage/gaoptout?hl=de>.

**Widerspruch gegen Datenerfassung**

Sie können die Erfassung Ihrer Daten durch Google Analytics verhindern, indem Sie auf folgenden Link klicken. Es wird ein Opt-Out-Cookie gesetzt, der die Erfassung Ihrer Daten bei zukünftigen Besuchen dieser Website verhindert: Google Analytics deaktivieren.

Mehr Informationen zum Umgang mit Nutzerdaten bei Google Analytics finden Sie in der Datenschutzerklärung von Google: <https://support.google.com/analytics/answer/6004245?hl=de>.

 **Auftragsdatenverarbeitung**

Wir haben mit Google einen Vertrag zur Auftragsdatenverarbeitung abgeschlossen und setzen die strengen Vorgaben der deutschen Datenschutzbehörden bei der Nutzung von Google Analytics vollständig um.

**Demografische Merkmale bei Google Analytics**

Diese Website nutzt die Funktion “demografische Merkmale” von Google Analytics. Dadurch können Berichte erstellt werden, die Aussagen zu Alter, Geschlecht und Interessen der Seitenbesucher enthalten. Diese Daten stammen aus interessenbezogener Werbung von Google sowie aus Besucherdaten von Drittanbietern. Diese Daten können keiner bestimmten Person zugeordnet werden. Sie können diese Funktion jederzeit über die Anzeigeneinstellungen in Ihrem Google-Konto deaktivieren oder die Erfassung Ihrer Daten durch Google Analytics wie im Punkt “Widerspruch gegen Datenerfassung��� dargestellt generell untersagen.

## 5\. Newsletter

### Newsletterdaten

Wenn Sie den auf der Website angebotenen Newsletter beziehen möchten, benötigen wir von Ihnen eine E-Mail-Adresse sowie Informationen, welche uns die Überprüfung gestatten, dass Sie der Inhaber der angegebenen E-Mail-Adresse sind und mit dem Empfang des Newsletters einverstanden sind. Weitere Daten werden nicht bzw. nur auf freiwilliger Basis erhoben. Diese Daten verwenden wir ausschließlich für den Versand der angeforderten Informationen und geben diese nicht an Dritte weiter.

Die Verarbeitung der in das Newsletteranmeldeformular eingegebenen Daten erfolgt ausschließlich auf Grundlage Ihrer Einwilligung (Art. 6 Abs. 1 lit. a DSGVO). Die erteilte Einwilligung zur Speicherung der Daten, der E-Mail-Adresse sowie deren Nutzung zum Versand des Newsletters können Sie jederzeit widerrufen, etwa über den "Austragen"-Link im Newsletter. Die Rechtmäßigkeit der bereits erfolgten Datenverarbeitungsvorgänge bleibt vom Widerruf unberührt.

Die von Ihnen zum Zwecke des Newsletter-Bezugs bei uns hinterlegten Daten werden von uns bis zu Ihrer Austragung aus dem Newsletter gespeichert und nach der Abbestellung des Newsletters gelöscht. Daten, die zu anderen Zwecken bei uns gespeichert wurden (z.B. E-Mail-Adressen für den Mitgliederbereich) bleiben hiervon unberührt.

### MailChimp

Diese Website nutzt die Dienste von MailChimp für den Versand von Newslettern. Anbieter ist die Rocket Science Group LLC, 675 Ponce De Leon Ave NE, Suite 5000, Atlanta, GA 30308, USA.

MailChimp ist ein Dienst, mit dem u.a. der Versand von Newslettern organisiert und analysiert werden kann. Wenn Sie Daten zum Zwecke des Newsletterbezugs eingeben (z.B. E-Mail-Adresse), werden diese auf den Servern von MailChimp in den USA gespeichert.

MailChimp verfügt über eine Zertifizierung nach dem “EU-US-Privacy-Shield”. Der “Privacy-Shield” ist ein Übereinkommen zwischen der Europäischen Union (EU) und den USA, das die Einhaltung europäischer Datenschutzstandards in den USA gewährleisten soll.

Mit Hilfe von MailChimp können wir unsere Newsletterkampagnen analysieren. Wenn Sie eine mit MailChimp versandte E-Mail öffnen, verbindet sich eine in der E-Mail enthaltene Datei (sog. web-beacon) mit den Servern von MailChimp in den USA. So kann festgestellt werden, ob eine Newsletter-Nachricht geöffnet und welche Links ggf. angeklickt wurden. Außerdem werden technische Informationen erfasst (z.B. Zeitpunkt des Abrufs, IP-Adresse, Browsertyp und Betriebssystem). Diese Informationen können nicht dem jeweiligen Newsletter-Empfänger zugeordnet werden. Sie dienen ausschließlich der statistischen Analyse von Newsletterkampagnen. Die Ergebnisse dieser Analysen können genutzt werden, um künftige Newsletter besser an die Interessen der Empfänger anzupassen.

Wenn Sie keine Analyse durch MailChimp wollen, müssen Sie den Newsletter abbestellen. Hierfür stellen wir in jeder Newsletternachricht einen entsprechenden Link zur Verfügung. Des Weiteren können Sie den Newsletter auch direkt auf der Website abbestellen.

Die Datenverarbeitung erfolgt auf Grundlage Ihrer Einwilligung (Art. 6 Abs. 1 lit. a DSGVO). Sie können diese Einwilligung jederzeit widerrufen, indem Sie den Newsletter abbestellen. Die Rechtmäßigkeit der bereits erfolgten Datenverarbeitungsvorgänge bleibt vom Widerruf unberührt.

Die von Ihnen zum Zwecke des Newsletter-Bezugs bei uns hinterlegten Daten werden von uns bis zu Ihrer Austragung aus dem Newsletter gespeichert und nach der Abbestellung des Newsletters sowohl von unseren Servern als auch von den Servern von MailChimp gelöscht. Daten, die zu anderen Zwecken bei uns gespeichert wurden (z.B. E-Mail-Adressen für den Mitgliederbereich) bleiben hiervon unberührt.

Näheres entnehmen Sie den Datenschutzbestimmungen von MailChimp unter: <https://mailchimp.com/legal/terms/>.

**Abschluss eines Data-Processing-Agreements**

Wir haben ein sog. „Data-Processing-Agreement“ mit MailChimp abgeschlossen, in dem wir MailChimp verpflichten, die Daten unserer Kunden zu schützen und sie nicht an Dritte weiterzugeben. Dieser Vertrag kann unter folgendem Link eingesehen werden: <https://mailchimp.com/legal/forms/data-processing-agreement/sample-agreement/>.

### Sparkpost

Diese Website nutzt die Dienste von Sparkpost für den Versand von Newslettern. Anbieter ist die Sparkpost Inc., 301 Howard St #1330, San Francisco, CA 94105, USA.

Sparkpost ist ein Dienst, mit dem u.a. der Versand von Newslettern organisiert und analysiert werden kann. Wenn Sie Daten zum Zwecke des Newsletterbezugs eingeben (z.B. E-Mail-Adresse), werden diese auf den Servern von Sparkpost in den USA gespeichert.

Sparkpost verfügt über eine Zertifizierung nach dem “EU-US-Privacy-Shield”. Der “Privacy-Shield” ist ein Übereinkommen zwischen der Europäischen Union (EU) und den USA, das die Einhaltung europäischer Datenschutzstandards in den USA gewährleisten soll.

Mit Hilfe von Sparkpost können wir unsere Newsletterkampagnen analysieren. Wenn Sie eine mit Sparkpost versandte E-Mail öffnen, verbindet sich eine in der E-Mail enthaltene Datei (sog. web-beacon) mit den Servern von MailChimp in den USA. So kann festgestellt werden, ob eine Newsletter-Nachricht geöffnet und welche Links ggf. angeklickt wurden. Außerdem werden technische Informationen erfasst (z.B. Zeitpunkt des Abrufs, IP-Adresse, Browsertyp und Betriebssystem). Diese Informationen können nicht dem jeweiligen Newsletter-Empfänger zugeordnet werden. Sie dienen ausschließlich der statistischen Analyse von Newsletterkampagnen. Die Ergebnisse dieser Analysen können genutzt werden, um künftige Newsletter besser an die Interessen der Empfänger anzupassen.

Wenn Sie keine Analyse durch Sparkpost wollen, müssen Sie den Newsletter abbestellen. Hierfür stellen wir in jeder Newsletternachricht einen entsprechenden Link zur Verfügung. Des Weiteren können Sie den Newsletter auch direkt auf der Website abbestellen.

Die Datenverarbeitung erfolgt auf Grundlage Ihrer Einwilligung (Art. 6 Abs. 1 lit. a DSGVO). Sie können diese Einwilligung jederzeit widerrufen, indem Sie den Newsletter abbestellen. Die Rechtmäßigkeit der bereits erfolgten Datenverarbeitungsvorgänge bleibt vom Widerruf unberührt.

Die von Ihnen zum Zwecke des Newsletter-Bezugs bei uns hinterlegten Daten werden von uns bis zu Ihrer Austragung aus dem Newsletter gespeichert und nach der Abbestellung des Newsletters sowohl von unseren Servern als auch von den Servern von MailChimp gelöscht. Daten, die zu anderen Zwecken bei uns gespeichert wurden (z.B. E-Mail-Adressen für den Mitgliederbereich) bleiben hiervon unberührt.

Näheres entnehmen Sie den Datenschutzbestimmungen von Sparkpost unter: <https://www.sparkpost.com/policies/privacy/>.

**Abschluss eines Data-Processing-Agreements**

Wir haben ein sog. „Data-Processing-Agreement“ mit Sparkpost abgeschlossen, in dem wir Sparkpost verpflichten, die Daten unserer Kunden zu schützen und sie nicht an Dritte weiterzugeben.

## 6\. Tools

### Google Web Fonts

Diese Seite nutzt zur einheitlichen Darstellung von Schriftarten so genannte Web Fonts, die von Google bereitgestellt werden. Beim Aufruf einer Seite lädt Ihr Browser die benötigten Web Fonts in ihren Browsercache, um Texte und Schriftarten korrekt anzuzeigen.

Zu diesem Zweck muss der von Ihnen verwendete Browser Verbindung zu den Servern von Google aufnehmen. Hierdurch erlangt Google Kenntnis darüber, dass über Ihre IP-Adresse unsere Website aufgerufen wurde. Die Nutzung von Google Web Fonts erfolgt im Interesse einer einheitlichen und ansprechenden Darstellung unserer Online-Angebote. Dies stellt ein berechtigtes Interesse im Sinne von Art. 6 Abs. 1 lit. f DSGVO dar.

Wenn Ihr Browser Web Fonts nicht unterstützt, wird eine Standardschrift von Ihrem Computer genutzt.

Weitere Informationen zu Google Web Fonts finden Sie unter <https://developers.google.com/fonts/faq> und in der Datenschutzerklärung von Google: <https://www.google.com/policies/privacy/>.

## 7\. Zahlungsanbieter

### PayPal

Auf unserer Website bieten wir u.a. die Bezahlung via PayPal an. Anbieter dieses Zahlungsdienstes ist die PayPal (Europe) S.à.r.l. et Cie, S.C.A., 22-24 Boulevard Royal, L-2449 Luxembourg (im Folgenden “PayPal”).

Wenn Sie die Bezahlung via PayPal auswählen, werden die von Ihnen eingegebenen Zahlungsdaten an PayPal übermittelt.

Die Übermittlung Ihrer Daten an PayPal erfolgt auf Grundlage von Art. 6 Abs. 1 lit. a DSGVO (Einwilligung) und Art. 6 Abs. 1 lit. b DSGVO (Verarbeitung zur Erfüllung eines Vertrags). Sie haben die Möglichkeit, Ihre Einwilligung zur Datenverarbeitung jederzeit zu widerrufen. Ein Widerruf wirkt sich auf die Wirksamkeit von in der Vergangenheit liegenden Datenverarbeitungsvorgängen nicht aus.
